alright dude today's idea cafe that's
awesome there's an echo day a today's
question is what are your thoughts
feeling on communism or Marxism
whichever you would like to answer it on
and I will participate flat
does anyone else have it was a bit
actually so it's not clear what you were
saying it's funny why it's actually so
many tabulator but all right I'm gonna
meet me in a moment I understand why
it's doing that it hasn't done that
before but would anybody like to take my
domestic experts questions well um it
looks like I'm not muted so maybe I'll
just start I guess the the sort of meta
thing for me on this is that this is one
of those instances where definitions
matter and it seems like most of the
conversations around communism Marxism
there there's never they never get to
find especially online when I was a
little kid you know like seventh grade
or something I remember reading the
Communist Manifesto for the first time
and you know what I thought that it was
going to be about and what it actually
ended up being about you know no almost
almost no connection and I feel like in
the end you know it's like everyone's
always speaking past each other here at
the on the the right hand or the right
side of the pectoral seems to define the
communism is meaning you know the
killing fields and or whatever possible
you know Venezuela and or it's like
certain very very specific horrible
things and it excludes
other other things where's I guess I
mean Marxism to me I you know even
though it's been a million years since
I've been in grad school and I have no
idea of what the Academy is actually
talking about it anymore you know I hear
the I hear the reports about it I don't
know that I trust what I hear people say
but you know marks to me Marxism is more
of a framework of analysis rather than a
an in the state of anything and you know
power relations and communism is never
existent so it's sort of a moot point
you know it's like this this in this you
know final stage of some sort of process
so I guess my feelings about it are
frustration the frustration that the
conversation is never grounded enough in
a shared you know whatever looks just a
little backwards start shared
definitions the idea that there's there
could be a critique in any way of of
capitalism I mean it seems fair enough
to me which doesn't mean I also think
that most of the conversation about
capitalism end up the same way where
nobody's defining their terms or saying
what they mean so I guess that's my
vague and non-committal interesting okay
yeah okay let me know if if the sound is
not coming through clearly yeah I can
relate to what you were sharing and
about defining of the concepts that is
definitely a very important thing for me
as well and at the same time I'm trying
to kind of expand that and think
what else what besides that is as
relevant for me in this thing and I
guess I want to turn even kind of more
generally to the human humans
interacting and not even maybe going
that far to the kind of defining the
terms but more like agreeing on the
intention of the conversation just why
are we talking why are we here in
general because I think that's a general
trend and part of a kind of a big issue
in our cultures is that we self express
we don't really communicate and the
different difference putting it out that
when I made self expressing like a
modern artist I don't even expect to be
understood maybe I'm just putting it out
there and just think about well that's
how I see it or how I frame it while
communication implies seeking that that
the message would get through and then I
would even get the feedback that it got
through so if if I don't see people
understanding me then it's my
responsibility to keep trying other ways
to send it but if people come to the
conversation and they don't explicitly
explicitly state that that's their
intention to communicate rather than
self express and they don't know why
they're there then I think very often
it's a futile endeavor and then more
specifically as a reaction to towards
the topic is that it's well for me it's
I'm already biased against those ideas
in a sense that I was born in the Soviet
Union in lessly I was raised while
seeing quite a lot of that and then
later after the independence hearing a
lot of bad stuff that was going on so
definitely I have a kind of a very much
like that concern of how will that be
implemented if there's again some kind
of attempt to introduce those ideas
especially if somebody follows the
principle rather than the practice
because there are lots of social ideas
kind of from democratic socialism to
social democracy all those things
they're kind of on that spectrum so
there's lots of stuff that is not pure
loser fair market and that means that
essentially we are experiencing some of
those aspects some some of the stuff
that is part of that framework that Marx
said and so well it is confusing to say
the least and it is kind of worrisome
when when even the let's say describing
that as a kind of a left side of the
spectrum although I don't subscribe to
the left and right that's just too
restrictive but if simplifying it in
those terms there is a lot of
disagreement and if you would just take
even among the Marxists leaning people
there's quite a bit of a kind of a
distinction from what I've seen between
kind of clear anarchists ideas and then
some other groups and so it's just an
it's since its kind of considered fringe
in the Western culture and it's not
really part of the overtones window
nobody really talks about those things
in kind of a very neutral terms and just
with curiosity it's more like you know
these are French people we don't really
care about their opinions so when we
hear so little it's difficult to know
what are the people how are the people
who are thinking of those things and
talking of those things so it's
difficult to relate unless you're
delving into YouTube and some other
places and really exploring it and give
more deeply you don't just don't know
about that and and I guess that that
makes it more confusing
and although I've looked into some of
those ideas and I'm curious and I'm
definitely leaning closer to the left
ideas because of some psychological
practices that are more empathetic more
inclusive more communitarian in a sense
it's it's still kind of concerning
remembering the history that
implementation is a difficult part you
know you can define something very
nicely in the vision but then how you're
getting there it's it's tricky and and
and I guess that's with many different
ideas not just economical and social
structure ones yeah so that's that's my
reaction thank you thank you I will
share since there's only three of us i'm
cherdon in all three so far the idea
cafes now um I don't know if I'm
repeating myself I probably am but with
my memory issues I never know um I think
there's a lot of beauty in communism and
Marxism as it is written out in a like
the idea of it not necessarily the
implementation of it if we look at that
beauty and ignore the atrocities that
have been committed under it we're doing
it a disservice because there's
something about the implementation of
these beautiful ideals that when forced
upon a population ends up with
atrocities and I think there are ways
for us to have the good without the bad
and it's not implementing it on a
massive scale it's doing it in a way
that's safe enough to try that's looking
at the individual piece how much do we
want to have personal autonomy and how
much can we have group coherence and how
can we work as a collective as a bigger
collective either globally or nationally
whatever scale were on in order to be
efficient without handing over our power
to a tiny group it clearly will never
hand power back because that I think
we've tried that and it doesn't work it
doesn't work under fascism it doesn't
work under you know debauch
using capitalism and it doesn't work
under communism so I think that there is
a lot of benefit to the ideals and I
also think that Marx died a hundred
years ago over a hundred years ago and
to hold him as the father of something
that he couldn't possibly understand how
it would implement in today's world with
technology with you know this global
society and so to hand over our power to
someone who died a hundred years ago and
say this must be written out in a letter
of the law doesn't work and to me throw
everything out doesn't work and I agree
with Anna that definitions definitely
help in discussions otherwise we're
doing that piece of like arguing with
what somebody didn't say instead
assuming that their definitions the same
as ours and we're kind of arguing our
definition before ever actually deciding
on one so those are my thoughts on it
and now we can all unmute and have a
discussion now that I'm sorry about all
the bean off-camera and being completely
discombobulated
much better without the echo yeah it was
okay no problem it feel like you're in
the room somewhere they're listing hmm
well just when you were saying these
things about Marx being like not
involved in those later implementations
I remembered another thought that I had
before that in a sense makes it also
less relevant what he said or didn't say
is that well he was just one person okay
well maybe with some of the people
thinking and it's not as he's some kind
of superhuman and we couldn't come up
with those ideas in a more appropriate
fashion so we don't even need to maybe
attach yourself to his name or whatever
we can use whatever resource we have we
can take all the ideas from wherever
rather than just putting it well mark
said that and maybe he was right on
whatever just focusing on that place and
location as if we are not empowered
enough
or a be capable enough of coming up
with those same maybe conclusions or
better ones yet it's so just like
leaving the guy alone the rest and then
find other ways to express what is
important to you rather than just okay
go read Marx or go drill read the Milton
or whatever Friedman it's kind of a yeah
to push back mm-hmm it and I think one
of the things that has often troubled me
in the in the discussions and I did not
grow up I mean I mainly grew up in the
States but a lot in Latin America as
well so there were several more or less
successful attempts but one of the
things that he did say that seems to be
almost always excluded from the
conversations was that you know
communism in his utopian ideal was
something that was going to happen after
capitalism after development it could
never happen while economies were
attempting to develop and most of the
places where there have been atrocious
misuses were economies that were very
much attempting to develop and not where
as yet when you look at you know the
northern the Nordic countries and you
know who already had developed meaning
that they had certain types of
infrastructure and they had certain
types of access to you know means of
international exchange that were not
available to economies that didn't and
that that that yields a completely
different outcome whereas economies that
you know anyway so this so it's sort of
like by excluding the some of the key
points you end up in conflating anyway I
think I think that the the process
of development matters and and hittin
and essentially we are talking about we
have to be talking about political
economy I mean if we're talking about
Marxism and communism it's not just you
know the arts there or something
so you know economic development matters
and in the countries and if we also
think about the the Nordic countries
they were also not as from to be okay
this is going to make me sound like yes
well anyway whatever they weren't as fun
to be colonial powers and the the the
reason that that matters is that if you
are getting your resources somewhere
that doesn't that don't where your local
population is not losing something so
like you know this was what happened
with the US you know where the the
United States came into being as a as a
colonias a as a colony that was
supplying things back to a central power
without rights within that larger
economy certain rights that those are
that those are some of them the missing
the missing ingredients and a whole lot
of the discussions that we you know who
has rights to what it's not just the
collective of a of a discussion group or
above or people that you could see in
your own country we end up with much
larger population frames than we admit
to in most of these discussions you know
it's like where's the closed system
where's the open system and we we often
miss mistake which one is which meaning
you know a closed economy that is only
some particular country versus oh you
mean like the boundaries are so vague so
it's difficult to define what we're
talking about no I mean in in economic
terms often the way that okay I have
absolutely no idea how
this how these sorts of conversations
would appear to you having grown up
within that system I guess I'm I'm very
unfortunately entrenched in a us Linda
Cole yeah well and just just a polemical
debate as opposed to and and I just I
see the edges where that tends to fall
apart and the and the things that are
almost always excluded so for instance
like the you like most of the Americans
that I speak to have very little
understanding of how well trade I mean
just just just to talk about trade like
they don't really understand what what
that means I don't know you know well
and I mentioned this in a text I have
literally not gonna sleep for 48 hours
and I'm just like it's something would
like this in my head it was like that's
my normal stance so forgot the beginning
of that sentence I trusted the intention
through your expression still kind of
stress and we can pick up something
about it some way I yield I don't know
what to say either it's funny I'm I also
didn't get a lot of sleep last night and
I require a lot and then coming on and
being discombobulated with the like
sound being off and and that kind of
thing I'm like what are we talking about
right Marxism communism yep this is my
third conversation so far this week on
this and I thought they were going to be
more divisive I thought that's why I
planned them and I'm like I don't even
know how to handle a divisive
conversation but we're gonna figure it
out as we go and then they weren't there
hasn't been a lot of disagreement there
hasn't been a lot of like I think we've
gotten to the underlining like here's
the pieces we lie
in it and we all admit that there's been
genocide and horrific account accounts
for it and I also love our global world
that like there are so many people who
have experienced communism who've
experienced capitalism who've
experienced moving from one to the other
and having parents that grew up in one
and offered that that insight and that
we live in that world where even if you
have one experience there are so many
experiences that surround you and being
open to that and hearing each other
because you know 20 people we could have
a conversation all having grown up in a
communist country and they're all gonna
have a completely different experience
from that based on their family
structure and their their their language
around it right and they're probably
their socioeconomic status even though
that shouldn't matter under communism
right that of course it does right
whether you grew up poor or whether your
family had power whether you had access
to those Goods and so I just wanted to
say that so if I get it correctly it was
in a way a pleasant surprise that there
was a lot of kind of shared ground and
also diversity of points of view still
kind of presenting aspects of it but
still a lot of commonality yeah I mean I
feel like most people want to find the
good in all of the systems that we have
tried so far on this planet and find a
way to create one that works for the
individual for the group for the globe
and if we can't do that right if game B
can't come together people who are
already drawn into game B and find that
common ground on something that is
divisive like communism what hope do we
have with the rest of the world who
isn't even looking for it right who
isn't even looking for that space but I
think I'm a this is my own bias being
the person who's trying to create idea
cafe that a lot of times it's the tool
it's the tool we're using and not
necessarily the people it's the fact
that people were typing out stuff and
reading into what people were saying
rather than visually see
each other but also maybe this brought
in the people who were more left-leaning
hmm I don't know more centrist or
centrist you had how many of these
discussions three so far and there's
another one oh yeah I think so yeah
there's been three of us needs which is
also kind of been because I find for the
idea cafe although four is what I'm
going for five is the maximum three
seems to be magic there is something
about three people having a conversation
in an idea cafe format that everyone
gets heard and there's a lot of time to
share and talk right because if it's
only half an hour and four people talk
that's 20 minutes then you have a
10-minute conversation and so you only
have a tiny bit of that so it's it's
nice finding the iterations that work
for for this process I would like to try
to tie in which I just heard you say and
kind of maybe kind of make a category
distinction it seems like there are
levels or layers so first talking about
the implementation of some kind of ideas
if you mentioned if we if we are kind of
failing in our group to find kind of
common ground about it then obviously
the rest people who are less engaged
they are maybe even less prepared for
that because they haven't investigated
that and and then kind of stepping back
if we can't even manage to talk about it
in a in a way you know kind of
constructively then there's even less
hope and and then you are pointing out
to the fact that it's maybe not so much
that we are not capable of talking but
that the medium itself is limiting us so
in the Facebook post it's two
antagonistic while when we're joining
and talking it's much easier because
we're connecting properly so so this
idea of a medium and I want to expand
that even further
just name the culture itself as a medium
where we have where the medium shapes
the message and and then obviously we
bring our culture into Facebook or into
these conversations and so then the
culture cultural shift naturally is a
kind of a first topic for me how do we
change the culture so we would be able
to have the conversations about how to
implement the changes mm-hmm kind of not
even talking about culture of maybe
economical sense of culture but just a
culture of relating just how we talk in
general with each other not only on
Facebook but just in principle because
there are prevalent programs around
everywhere and they just get triggered
by various topics that are more hot like
hot potatoes to throw around but our
attitudes towards behavior towards each
other and and maybe also not seeing a
culture for what it is not recognizing
the effect that it has on us mmm the
part of this is that we recognize each
other as embodied people right we're not
just letters on a screen like we each
have faces and there we have and I think
that that that is something that I'm
very you know ultimately concerned about
you know or are we do do we understand
and and some of my work is actually
conducting focus groups so I am I'm in
these sorts of forum a lot a lot a lot a
lot and and I'm on all sorts of topics
from aids to politics to to you know
many different things and on the one
hand and and often they're people that
are like behind behind a mirror behind
me and there and and the people who
don't do these sorts of things a lot are
always shocked by what people will say
openly with each other you know people
who don't know each other or will
to say when they actually see each other
as opposed to you know that undefined
other or the projected other the you
know that that's sort of thinking I
think that there really is something
about you know us as beings in a
relating that is it gives a lot of cause
for hope you know when we when we
reduced to stereotypes it's much easier
to to project idiocy and or you know
vile intentions or whatever it is you're
just inconsiderateness like you don't
care about me maybe you're a good person
but you just don't care about yeah I
mean I think this space is what I'm
hoping I mean this is the space I'm
plane and this is like try to become how
do we create social media that's
designed for connection real connection
we're not trying to troll we're not
trying to increase the divisive nough so
it increases profit we're actually
trying to increase connection and bring
people together and find that common
ground and part of that is going to be
we need to have conflict to figure that
out
alright they're like this wasn't
conflict enough like it's like how do I
like but which is beautiful like I love
that it hasn't been but I'm like but I
was looking for a little bit to be able
to see what that was like and have it
fall apart so you could build it back up
and I don't
ok and so we have about two more minutes
before the 30 minute mark everyone wants
to kind of wrap up their their thoughts
and then we can stop recording and vote
slash whatever you go by the broadcast
so maybe maybe I'll start my wrap-up
would be that at least from this
conversation it seems that the topic
isn't really maybe not not that it's not
an issue but it's like not the first
issue and it just becomes a red flag in
the conversations about the bigger issue
that somebody is not caring about me
enough and introducing some ideas which
might penetrate my boundaries or
whatever and therefore I need to step up
and defend whatever I care about because
I don't I don't trust this space to be
safe enough for me I suspect that that's
kind of a one of the primary things that
it the if it's a certain topic arises
it's a signal for me to kind of strain
myself and start go on a offensive
defense and and that I guess in terms of
what you just mentioned in terms of that
creation of the of the conversation and
it being a bit too easy here not not
enough of a challenge
maybe the purpose of this not being a
challenge is to actually I just thought
it might be just to give you hope that
actually you don't even need a challenge
maybe maybe it's better just to learn
not to see the challenge in the text
world as well and just perceive it as a
well the friendly person that I am sure
I would connect to on that visual level
and direct conversation is just
communicating in a way that I need to
learn to understand as actually saying
that everything is okay we're talking
like that thank you thank you I think I
like that I like um I know for me my own
interpersonal work I need to figure out
how to do that with text it's easier for
me to do that with video it's not as
easy with text both I read into my own
wording like what are they gonna read
into it and trying to find 15 layers and
answer them before they even ask it and
then I do read into other people when
they're typing I don't assume
intelligence and kindness and
sovereignty in the same way I do on
video so thank you for that
Glenda's yeah I wonder if it's possible
through text I you know without without
seeing someone I mean at least in
facebook you can sometimes see a picture
of somebody so you you remember there's
a person but and not just a threat yeah
I guess there there are a couple of
people in the in the in the wider world
for what uh oh gosh what's the rally
point in the game
you know it's a lot of the same people
that that come across them and I can
imagine this conversation might have
been different if you know a couple of
people I'm thinking of were in the mix
and I would have loved that to know you
know to a certain extent I guess mainly
for the exact same reasons that we've
ultimately come to because you know
would like to see the humanity and would
like to know that we're all you know
coming into the same page
anyway then Julie can I just say kudos
to you you know super kudos to you for
doing this and thank you I've enjoyed it
this has been a fun week I was okay so
I'm gonna say goodbye to YouTube if we
do decide to publish it and we can stop
broadcasting and discuss that I YouTube